John Josef "Sef" Kloninger

635 Central Ave. Menlo Park, CA, 94025 cell: 650-644-8191 mail: sefklon@gmail.com blog: sef.kloninger.com

Summary

VP of Engineering or Technical Operations building meaningful and interesting Internet software. I like fast systems and rooting out wasted cycles. I use metrics to drive improvement, the truth can usually be found in production. I like startup pace. I judge engineering management (myself) by asking: are engineers working hard, working on the right things, and in right way.

I have experience building and operating distributed systems with thousands of servers over complex networks. I've lead core engineering and ops groups at Akamai, VMware, and Ning. Largest team managed was 140 engineers across three locations. BS Computer Science, Stanford 1993.

Work Experience

Ning (acquired by Glam Media, Dec 2011) Palo Alto, CA VP Infrastructure Engineering and Operations (12/2010-4/2012)

Operations. Oversaw the team running a medium-sized platform: 100K sites, 140M requests/day, 60M uniques/month, 240TB of user-generated content. Maintained four nines of availability. Established set of core technical metrics: incidents, availability, and performance. Built a mini-NOC. Defended DDoS attacks by running build vs. buy analysis, then negotiating contract with service provider.

Infrastructure. Line managed senior engineers on the core Ning platform: relational and key/value content, blob storage, messaging, service discovery, mail, activity, and API's. ~50 RESTful Java services. Ran project to convert Oracle to sharded MySQL. Improved performance by restructuring JS and CSS and targeted rewrites. Responsible for development and support of the Ning API.

VMware, Desktop Virtualization Senior Director, Desktop Engineering

Palo Alto, CA (5/2008-12/2010)

Built products using server and client virtualization to disrupt how corporate Windows desktops are deployed and managed. Grew from managing one group to leading engineering for the Desktop Business Unit: 130 engineers in the US, UK, India, China. Managed managers, directors, and three principal engineers (VMware's most senior technical role).

Delivered major releases that grew Desktop from \$10M to \$100M. Owned development for enterprise desktop: VMware View for remote virtual desktops, and ThinApp for Windows appplication virtualization. Also two personal desktop packaged products: Workstation on Windows and Linux, and Fusion on Mac. Technical sponsor of two strategic transactions: acquisition of RTO Software for profile virtualization and OEM of Teradici's PCoIP remote display protocol.

Akamai Technologies

San Mateo, CA (2007-08)

Senior Director, Service Performance (2005-08)

Cambridge, MA (1999-07)

Founded the Service Performance group in Networks & Operations for advanced ops and high-touch customer engagements. Grew organization from six to 35 engineers and architects in US and India.

Improve service reliability by driving bulletproofing and scaling initiatives. Managed Akamai's incident response process. Define and measure core platform quality metrics, presented quarterly to CEO and Chief Scientist. Owned high-touch customer escalations and events, including: 2006 Olympics, March Madness, Microsoft patch Tuesdays, Hulu's launch, and Apple iPhone launch. Designed a unique cache hierarchy setup for long-tail social networking content.

Director and Senior Director, Engineering (1999-05)

Engineering Manager of 20-50 engineers and managers. Led technical hiring during company growth, then managed transitions and motivated teams during staff reductions. Mentor to other managers, senior engineers, and architects. Established processes for development, QA, and release engineering. Oversaw technical integration of two acquired companies.

Hands-on technical leader of Akamai's core technology. Handled many urgent service incidents; one of five crisis managers called in for the big problems. Experience includes:

- Communication infra.
- Security systems
- HTTP and DNS servers

- Load balancing
- Coherence protocols
- Fault tolerance systems

- Linux kernel
- Operations tools
- System and unit testing

Senior Software Engineer (1999)

Lead engineer on HTTP content server. Scaled technology and features for rapid pre-IPO growth.

FarSight Financial Services Senior Performance Engineer

Cambridge, MA (1998-99)

Enhanced performance of a website for retail on-line stock trading. Profiled systems, rewrote critical code paths (C++), and optimized database queries and schemas (Sybase).

Venturcom

Cambridge, MA (1996-98)

Principal Software Engineer

Principal architect, engineer, and team lead of Component Integrator, a tool for customizing and embedding Windows NT and CE. Product bought by Microsoft, later released as the Windows Embedded Studio. Venturcom eventually became Ardence, acquired by Citrix.

McKinsey & Company, IT Principal Software Engineer

Cambridge, MA (1993-96)

Led development of client/server human resource system for internal use. Enhanced and optimized custom database replication system (Oracle). Attended week-long training sessions on communication skills, writing, and problem solving.

Veritas Software

Santa Clara, CA (1990-93)

Software Engineer (Part-Time)

Developed and tested Visual Administrator tool suite (C, Motif, Xt).

Patents

- Content Delivery Network (CDN) Content Server Request Mechanism With Metadata Framework Support (7,240,100)
- Internet content delivery service with third party cache interface support (7,010,578)
- Enterprise Content Delivery Network Having a Central Controller For Coordinating a Set Of Content Servers (10/437,588)
- System and Apparatus For, and Method Of, Controlling Bandwidth On a Network Link Within an Enterprise Content Delivery Network (pending)

Education

Stanford University, B.S. Computer Science, 1993

Research: "Verification of SCI Cache Coherence Protocol" under Prof. David Dill.

Apr 2012